[Music]
[Applause]
n
[Music]
for
good
um so um tonight we'll continue our talk
about uh what is Nana and how to get
there and we've been talking for two
nights about that and um
I don't know somehow for me the word
Nana has a very beautiful feel to it
like the first time I heard it when I
was a kid I was like immediately
attracted to the word Nirvana I don't
know why I think many people are like
that many people feel like that about
the word
nana so we had an interesting question
last night and uh Krishna right asked
uh can you drop drop out of Nirvana
after you reach nirvana can you drop out
of Nirvana and and we've seen uh in this
class uh Nirvana defined in the ancient
Classics of Buddhism as they
call it means to repeat it means to
remove all the negative emotions in your
mind
forever uh because you have seen
Ultimate Reality directly okay due to
seeing ultimate dark uh reality
directly so then there are a lot of
opinions uh in the Buddhist schools in
fact I think you can say that the
difference between all the Buddhist
schools is what they think Ultimate
Reality is see so you could almost say
you know today we went over the three
schools
of viant and and and I was thinking in
Buddhism we have uh there are four Great
Schools of Tibet
but there are also four Great Schools of
ancient India which are different uh and
the four Great Schools of ancient India
really they differ in their idea of what
is Ultimate Reality okay and
um the point is that if you get it right
if you understand Ultimate Reality
correctly which is not so
difficult uh then it gives you the power
as nothing else can to remove your uh
own negative emotions uh permanently and
forever and then I don't know if I don't
think everyone was here from the
beginning but the first night I was
saying you know let's all try to
identify our number one negative emotion
you know and um and I was saying for me
it was jealousy you know and I'm quite
good at it uh after many years of
practice you know like we have sness
where we try to develop positive
qualities but but really we're
meditating all day on our on our cles
right so mine are highly
evolved and uh my jealousy is highly
well so you know I thought it Swami G
said it's not good to talk about
cookbooks if you don't taste the food
and I he made me embarrassed I thought
oh I if I'm teaching you about Nirvana
maybe I should try to think about
reaching it myself and uh then I was I
was exploring my own mind in the last
week you know and I was like in a way
that I never have before and you know
I've been meditating for I don't know 40
years or something and so I I was like
oh I have this big jealousy in my mind
you that's so big and it's so obvious uh
the minute I started
watching I was like struck by how much
of the day was devoted to jealousy you
and then uh I I was talking to some
people tonight my jealousy is like this
I I meet I have a mind and it's almost
like an empty
skull and then objects come and go from
my skull during the day you know I I
went to sw's S Class yoga class so I had
these events
of a class and there were people moving
through the class and I was watching
people being jealous
selectively and um and then uh objects
were moving objects were swimming
through the medium of my mind like fish
in a aquarium up here you know objects
were coming and going and then I started
to feel jealousy towards someone or or
competitiveness or like that like are
they better than me had this Asma you
know and then suddenly the
water in the head got dark I mean I I
was just first aware of it my whole mind
got dark like a shadow like a very
uh
sad Shadow over the water of my mind and
then for a few minutes I couldn't think
straight and I wasn't happy and my
breath was off in in the
ASA uh it was
noticeable and and then I realized I
just live like that most of the day and
I don't really notice it you know
and uh so that was I was I was asking
you guys to try
to uh catch your own mind at your
favorite negative emotions so I'm asking
you if you're in this talk little talk
every night let's try you know like
tomorrow morning when you do your
meditation
just go into the history of your life
and your recent life and and see what
kind of negative emotion you've been
specializing in because if you could
remove it or if you could get a little
bit of relief from it some in in
Buddhism they call uh Nirvana Shanti
sometimes of sha in tibetan and Shanti
has two meanings one is uh you know
feeling happy and contented but the
other is to extinguish a fire to put out
a fire and uh I I think if you do this
little exercise try to locate in your
mind your worst mental hit during the
day and and just and just watch it uh
tomorrow and see how many times it comes
up and then see how it makes you feel
just do that okay just do that you're
supposed to have done that already
actually uh The Next Step would be what
I'd like you to do for tomorrow is is uh
try
to try to get in touch with what the
opposite feels like okay try to get in
touch with what the opposite feels like
so for me uh rarely I will not be
jealous of someone I will actually
appreciate and what do you call
celebrate their good qualities like I
don't know why but I'm able to do it
with swy like I was jealous of him at
the
beginning but now for some reason it has
mowed into some
uh intense appreciation for his uh his
effort that he really an asham like this
is not kept together by organizational
things it's the willpower of a few
people and if they lose that willpower
the place just falls apart it just
disappears it's not the treasur and the
vice president and you know the policies
and the procedures it's not done it's
that there has to be a core of people
who really believe in what's going on
here and and they hold the asham
together it's willpower and and then
sometimes you see it leave a place and
then the place dies you know but you
have this what I see in in the Swami
serence is this intense willpower it
never occurred to any of you that there
might not be any programs next year
right it just never occurred to you you
were thinking how to pay for it or you
know how to clean up after the yes but
you weren't thinking it's unimaginable
that these swes wouldn't have the
willpower to keep this place going you
see and that's all that keeps it going
so I appreciate that and I admire it and
it's rare in the world so imagine how
try to do the opposite okay if you're an
angry
person you know if your favorite
Affliction is anger and and try to be
exceptionally patient with someone
tomorrow about something and just I want
you to just observe how it feels okay
I'm not asking you to keep it up or
anything I just want you to see how how
it feels compared to the anger that's
all and if you have low self-esteem then
try to comprehend that uh for every
person sitting here listening to these
holy things there are about 90 million
other people who are not and maybe
you're a little special okay really I
mean just try to
get a little feeling of the opposite
okay which is true in the Tibetan
scriptures
the the antidote for low self-esteem is
to just think of the odds of you getting
here which are about zero you know for
you to be one of the swamis here or
brahmachari here or chitana here or
something is uh you are one out of
what 10 million people you know and and
if you then to have low self-esteem
about the coolest person out of 10
million people is kind of
weird uh and know in our scriptures
you're just supposed to review how lucky
you are how you're unique each person
here is unique you got here somehow
through all the weird things of life you
got here and you're special you're very
extraordinary there's no uh arguing with
it it's obvious it's a
statistical okay you're just uh unique
out of 10 million people
that so what I'd like you to do tomorrow
is try to do the opposite all right if
your problem is anger then do some
patience uh and I just want you to
observe how it feels uh if your problem
is no self-esteem uh spend some time on
thinking that you are one in 10 million
which is the truth and you can't deny it
and just and just Savor that feeling for
a while feel the difference if you are
extremely jealous of every single person
you ever meet if you get jealous for
someone for their
sandals uh
then then uh try to just appreciate what
someone else is doing like the The
Willpower that keeps this place going
you know just appreciate somebody
else's uh high goodas high
qualties tomorrow okay so that's your
meditation assignment tomorrow
okay so I was uh I was still thinking
about your question yesterday in Chris
question and he said he said is it
possible to reach nirvana which now you
know means to uh eliminate your mental
your negative emotions forever okay the
the classical definition of nirvana
which is not the same as
Enlightenment uh is it's lower than
Enlightenment is to remove your negative
emotions
forever which is tied up with overcoming
sansara it's the same thing really and
we'll talk about that maybe tomorrow but
um if we
Define uh
Nirvana as the as removing your negative
emotions forever because
what because what yeah because you Hadi
talked about it today because you had a
direct experience of Ultimate Reality
okay that's the definition of NADA the
first part is easy right getting rid of
your negative emotions the second part
is a question
uh because you saw Ultimate Reality
directly so you know if I were you and
if I were me if I were locked up in this
aquarium with dirty water all day of
jealousy then I would be asking the
question what yeah how do you see
Ultimate Reality like what is Ultimate
Reality how do you see it cuz cuz then
you could just turn off your anger or
turn off your low self-esteem or you
know jealousy would be free of 80% of
your hard disk you know know uh no
really you know how fast the computer
runs when you take off half the stuff
imagine your mind like that take off
that's where people get all those cities
and B booties and all that cool stuff
they just they just freed up a lot of
the hard drive uh cuz they don't have
jealousy like I spend a lot of my day
being jealous and if suddenly I wasn't
spending that time like what can I do
you know it'd be interesting so
uh it's worth it we should try we should
talk tonight about what does it mean to
see Ultimate Reality because the answer
to krishna's
question sh Krishna
sh it used to be
Krishna anyway the answer he asked the
question can you fall out about it and
then I gave sort of a short answer uh
but the long answer the real answer is
much longer and I thought to do it
tonight the idea
is if you see an Ultimate Reality
directly which turns out to not be
really
ultimate can you drop out you will drop
out okay so then there's this huge
discussion
of of things that we thought were
Ultimate Reality but turned out not to
be okay why would we want to spend the
next I don't know half hour on
discussing an an Ultimate Reality which
turned out to not be the Ultimate
Reality yeah we want to avoid uh traps
okay like there are
presentations uh there are teachings
that will say here's what Ultimate
Reality is right and then you get good
at it and you master
and you see it directly and then it
doesn't stop your jealousy and then it
turns out not to be ultimate okay that's
where I'm trying to go I'm trying to say
there have been many many versions of
Ultimate Reality in the history of
Buddhism and as an exercise we always
study the mistaken ones first uh in the
monastery we always the teachers always
go through the wrong ultimate realities
first because then you don't then you if
you start thinking like that you just
stop yourself and you say oh yeah that
was number four and they that's why it's
not Ultimate Reality okay so what I'd
like to do tonight it's uh
six uh versions of Ultimate Reality and
only one of them is the real one and the
other five are ultimate realities that
you're going to flirt with in your in
your spiritual career and then you will
remember tonight and you will remember
that you should go a little further okay
so these are ultimate realities in
in we we gave well I how to
start Ultimate Reality is the absence of
something that was never
there okay Ultimate Reality is the
absence of something that was never
there okay it's a negative it's the
absence of something is there a
two-headed 14 ft purple elephant
rampaging through this room at this
moment no yes or no no he always
answered somebody else answered no there
isn't okay I mean nobody even turned
around to
check uh right if I had said is there a
baby elephant gray single head you know
walking into this you would look around
but if I said purple two-headed you know
18 ft tall then nobody even looks around
why why there's no such thing okay there
is no such and you know it so you're not
like fighting you're going to get
trampled okay you didn't even think
about that nobody went like
this uh it never existed so so Ultimate
Reality is the absence get this of
something which was never
there all right and we'll give an
example right yesterday we talked about
uh someone comes up to you and says
you're stupid J Michael okay and then
your natural reaction is you you say you
know you're stupid okay and then we said
that was proof that you are stupid
stupid as they accused you of being uh
because by by by answering you're stupid
you're planting a karmic seed to have
another person next week call you stupid
and that's SAR that's a cycle uh you
call somebody stupid that creates a
chronic seat in your mind next week
somebody comes up to you and calls you
stupid you answer them and say you know
you're stupid you plant a new caric
scene and then they come back again and
then you respond again and then that's a
big cycle okay that's SAR that's the
only meaning of s stupid circles okay
um and we said that um when the person
first called you
stupid you could
consider and we're going to do that as a
meditation later looking at them and and
the person you first feel bad about
right the person who called you
stupid okay get this okay listen the
person who called you stupid who was not
coming from you got it is it in your
mind I'll say it one more time the
person who called you stupid who is not
coming from you calling somebody else
stupid before what's that person look
like exist they don't exist okay in
Tibet they say what do the antlers on a
rabbit look like how long are
they how many inches long are antlers on
rabbits you know and then you just say
well they don't they don't have any okay
the
person whom you feel angry towards
doesn't even
exist and never did
okay and that thinking they exist is
required to plant a proper negative
Karma and that's a viya got it that's
all there never was a person there who
didn't come from you and thinking they
are not coming from you is a vid and
only with a vid could you say to
them no you're stupid right because a
person with Vidya would refrain from
saying stupid because they want the
person to go
away all right okay got it you ready
okay so you have to understand you have
to get the sense and I know it's late
and I know we all had a hard day and it
was hot I don't care what for J
said we all experienced it the
same try to wrap your mind around this
thing ultimate reality is the absence of
a person who calls you stupid who's not
coming from you comfortable is it
comfortable in the monastery they say de
de
means you know is it comfortable you
okay with that Ultimate Reality is the
absence in this room of anyone who's not
coming from what you did last
week got it yes okay and that does that
help you cope when a person calls you
stupid that's the whole point of of
studying Ultimate
Reality whatever Ultimate Reality is it
should help you cope with a person who
calls you stupid and eventually remove
all your anger completely you see if you
really Define Ultimate Reality correctly
it should be something which immediately
helps you to be a happier person got it
if you understand that Ultimate Reality
means that the guy who calls you stupid
came from you calling people stupid last
week then that will make you a happier
person CU you'll stop calling people
stupid and it'll make the people around
you happier too okay that's you know
you've got the real Ultimate Reality
when it when it's helpful okay when it
makes you happier okay so now we're
going to go on a little
trip uh among the lower ultimate
realities that have been taught in
Buddhism okay who who first taught them
who first lied and taught ultimate
realities that weren't ultimate
realities
G no which historical person Buddha
Buddha the Buddha okay the Buddha taught
five ultimate realities that weren't in
different scriptures he described five
versions of Ultimate Reality that were
wrong
why why would somebody say perverting
marar is the only way to go
you had it in class today excuse
me why would somebody say forver Marg is
the only way to
go no cuz people weren't ready for new
maret okay that's all so Lord Buddha
himself taught five things that Z real
which are not because he was trying to
get SW G was speaking very beautifully
today about Lord Krishna wanting to get
to use Karma Yoga to get arj's mind to a
point finally where he was ready for
yoga okay got it like he just taught
lower things to Arjuna until finally
Arjun was ready to hear the real thing
got it so in buddhis in the same Halles
you you speak to your audience and if
you don't you have done a bad de you see
uh you you morph to your audience so
Lord budow was very good at it uh so
here here they are ready these are five
versions of Ultimate Reality that are
not but you will hear them and and and
the next time you hear them you're going
to say no no I got to go further I got
to go further ready here's the first one
[Music]
say okay that means
a person who's yelling at you who's
going to last
forever okay a person in your life who
who who who regularly calls you stupid
who is going to be around
forever is there such a
thing no I mean luckily all the bad
people you've ever met I mean most of
them have died or gone away you know
they just do that okay all right we all
get old we all move out we move we're we
nothing last forever okay you ready this
two will pass uh Abraham Lincoln was in
the middle of the Civil War and somebody
said to him is there anything good about
this war and he said only one thing and
he said what he said this too will pass
this will also pass this thing will pass
okay
so means is there a person who calls you
stupid who's going to be around 50 years
from now calling you
stupid
hopefully you know no I mean just people
are torn apart by events and Karma and
and you know you can't stay with the
ones you love and luckily you catch Ste
the ones you hate also they just go in
you know so uh to perceive the Ultimate
Reality of of a person who's calling you
stupid in the lowest School of Buddhism
which is Abid school okay
is to say uh the person who's going to
last forever calling you stupid is there
such a person no it's exactly the same
as a two-headed purple elephant running
through this room got it got it Ultimate
Reality is the absence of something
which could never be and in the lowest
School of Buddhism they say Ultimate
Reality is the absence of a person who's
hurting you who's going to last forever
cuz they always go away
you know sooner or later they always go
away question two questions for you
ready these are important two important
questions for
you number one is it helpful in a
stressful situation with someone who's
criticizing you to think this two will
pass is it helpful it's helpful okay
does it stop your anger
forever no it'll work for a while we
call it a bandaid it's a temporary
okay you can stare at this person I do
it all the time somebody's like yelling
at me unreasonably always
unreasonably which if you think about it
would mean I don't deserve it which is
not possible uh for a Buddhist or Hindu
there's no such thing at any rate it
it's always undeserved and and I'm the
person is in my face and they are like
growling and then I'm like sometimes the
best I can do the farthest I can go in
my view of the of Ultimate Reality is
okay he's got to stop sooner or later
and he's got to have lunch he's got to
go to the toilet you know at some point
he'll stop I just have to stand here if
I just stand here long enough he'll he
has to go to the bathroom or something
sooner or later he'll this two will pass
that's all I can do I can't think
anything higher than that that's okay
okay that's okay that's a noral reality
it does does not take you to nervon it
does not stop your anger forever but it
helps okay one more point this is very
important okay one more Point these
lower versions of Ultimate Reality keep
you out of trouble until you can get to
the real one got it okay they're useful
okay at least they keep you from yelling
back and then you make a few more kic
points that might put you in a position
where someone can Contin chose n yoga
got it
okay Roger yoga okay so they're good
they're good uh they're temporary relief
like an Asin and they also kind of keep
your mind
CH Swami
said they keep your mind pure enough
that if you if someone taught you the
real Ultimate Reality you would get
it okay cuz you you were in the place of
the lower one for a while got it that's
number one okay number two I don't have
much time this is a race against the
clock
um
[Music]
say this means um when a person is in
your face yelling if you want to go a
bit higher on the Ultimate Reality
ladder the versions of What Ultimate
Reality is just
think where is the other person whose
actions I could control at this
moment where is the person calling me
stupid Whose actions I could control at
this moment it's the question of control
how much control do you have as a karma
is ripening no as a sansara is FL
flowering in the moment that a sansara
is flowering how how much control do you
have about the
situation you can control the next week
or the next few days you can say I'm not
going to get angry uh you know I won't
plant a new seed next week there won't
be anybody in my face but but no school
of Hindus and or Buddhism would say you
could control it in the moment you
cannot once it has opened once the karma
has opened nobody can control it okay so
you can take refuge that's a Buddhist
Refuge right you can take comfort in the
fact that
very very famous quotation by Master
Shan in the the engaging in the Deeds of
a what is it called anyway to the body
gu to the this like that's a good TR so
he said you know this is really original
right he said look if you can do
something about it do it then what did
he say after
that you can't do anything about it just
chill you know you can't do anything
about it just chill okay that's
worldview number two all right that's
that's Ultimate Reality number two this
is out of my control the karma is is is
opening in my mind at this moment I
don't have any control I can't stop it
so just relax if you can talk The person
into believing you're not stupid didn't
do so calmly and if they won't listen to
you then just let it go okay is that
helpful is it all will it stop your
negative emotions
for no you know that you've tried it
okay and we still have I still have mine
okay so that's that's Ultimate Reality
too the absence of a person who can be
controlled by you in the current
moment is Ultimate Reality verion number
two okay we don't have given that karma
is rening we don't have current control
we have future
control it's only future suffering I can
I can deal with okay an the stuff that
hasn't come yet I can I have control but
not still happening right that's the
point of that Sher right of that verse
okay
three I think I'm going to make it uh
number three uh
say you guys are sleeping it's easier to
teach tell say
[Music]
um this is delicate
okay who put when a person is calling
you stupid who put you
there you you by your karma by your
actions towards others who put them
there you who created the interaction
between you subject object that
interaction of the two who created the
subject G Michael getting called stupid
who created
that Michael who created the person
calling him
stupid who who made person number two
bump into person number
one
okay everything about the interaction
all the the whole we call it the three
Spirits right of course the the three
elements of a of an interaction are are
all being created from one karmic seat
and that's a big teaching of the Mind
only School of Buddhism okay they call
it sampo or
jatra uh they have a very interesting
belief try to get this okay uh you call
someone stupid in the past my elbow is
the past okay and then time goes
on and the seed the sansar ripens in the
Bas ripens in the mind
and then it comes out it you can do
Vishnu
mudra I always forget it but when I come
back I
remember through it then then it ripens
the seat ripens right into what a
subject and an object okay one seed one
Karma one
action splits into an object and a
subject K she Michael
and the person call me stupid okay
the stupid person
right
okay okay got it one see when it opens
it splits into me and the person kind is
stupid who brought him to me it was G
Michael okay uh now I have to also say
that in this school they believe that's
all happening inside your mind there is
no outer guy there is no it's just all
one SE that uh what do you call split
within your own mind okay is it helpful
to think like that I brought the guy
here I brought the guy into the room
yeah okay and I brought who into the
room me one person forced G Michael into
the room and one person standing at the
other door pushed the guy into the room
who who was the both people it was me
okay and then we're forced to have this
interaction unpleasant interaction right
who's who Who's the I don't know bad guy
it's me okay I I climed the that S I
made him come to me I forced him to come
to me okay think about that is it
helpful when someone's screaming at you
yeah I mean you don't blame them it's
the water on the bathroom floor syndrome
right as long as you know you're the one
who spilled the water there it's not so
bad and right you know I mean you spill
water on the floor and you're leaving
the bathroom cuz you're in a rush to get
this SG tar and you look down you see
the water and you say well you know a
little bit is not going to hurt
anybody is it true and then when you
step in and step in that water you're
like who's the stupid person and then
you you understand it was yourself then
you're much more uh
forgiving cuz it's few I got it so what
were we on number three three okay the
person abusing you has split off from a
single seed which also created you
inside your own mind now the inside your
own mind part is
wrong okay that can be
disproven uh and that's the wrong part
of this view because the rest is not so
bad the rest is pretty
good s
how we're getting there he asked how can
you disprove that we're going to get
there okay R to
number
say
[Music]
not is is an old s
okay I'll give an example uh often I
have people at my I worked in a huge
corporation I built a huge corporation
we had 800 workers in New York we had
10,000 other workers it started with
nothing uh and and there were many cases
uh when I would be sitting in my office
and somebody uh like the one of the
owners of the company would burst into
my room and say Michael you're really
stupid
you know and I'd say why and they'd say
you forgot this order for JC Penny and
10,000 diamonds and they already have
the advertisement in the New York Times
and they don't have any diamonds cuz you
didn't buy them yet okay the the stores
don't have what they already advertising
in the New York Times and it's your
fault you know and then I feel upset
right and then there's all these other
vice presidents in the room who are very
jealous of me so how do they
feel yeah like
finally somebody figured out you know
the truth
and so there's almost there's almost no
bad thing that ever happens to you that
someone else might not perceive as
desirable right so you talk to about it
today about the Heat and that someone
who's flying in from you know
Pittsburgh might think it was quite nice
here today okay because they've been
cold for a couple months uh or years I
don't know that's Montreal okay I that's
like close to the North Pole I know
um
so when the person's screaming at you
right you can always think that maybe
their
wife loves them maybe their wife finds
them lovable
someone would find this enjoyable you
know I have this theory that any way you
could um destroy a dish in
cooking any uh way you could abuse a
dish is probably the way it's cooked
somewhere you see what I mean I always
tell people like like they burn they
burn my doll you know and it tastes like
charcoal and I say I'm sure there's a
planet where
good Mothers burn the
dog right somebody would find it taste
good I think so so would that comfort
you when someone's calling you stupid to
think that somebody loves
them is it true yeah would it help to
think well somebody finds them lovable
everybody finds somebody lovable I mean
everybody's found lovable by somebody
right so does that help to think it that
way that's okay
okay uh if you want to know the literal
meaning of the
term
means nothing is named what it is
naturally names are not applied by by
Nature they are inventions they are
artificial uh the way you perceive an
event is not uh natural it's being uh
concocted by your mind someone else
might be perceiving the event as a quite
positive thing because they have
different caric seats no event is BN by
Nature uh it's perceived that way by
somebody because of their own coming
seats all right that's number four four
we're almost there we're going to make
it for
[Music]
sure are you ready
number five lower half of the middleway
school okay uh which are almost correct
okay how to say this
one long man long man means uh a state
of p a a mind which is not affected by
other circumstances such as drugs
alcohol extreme anger a mind which is
perceiving its object
correctly an object appears to that kind
of a state of mind
sh uh that's not all it takes for a
thing to exist is just to appear to an
unaffected state of perception there's
more what a you
[Music]
that thing must have some nature of its
own okay that thing must be one way or
another on its own there has to be both
there has to
be let
me your favorite song the best rock and
roll song in the
world just think about it cowgirl in the
St
byi in my
right the best rock and
roll right uh is there a song There Is
is it a song I mean it is a song it's on
his first album first Sol second I don't
second
um does everyone perceive it as the best
song
no it's just education it's of
[Laughter]
education is there a song appearing to
me when I play the song yes or no do I
interpret it as a good song myself yes I
do
uh so they say both of those things are
necessary in an act of deception there
must be something there
the like 50% must be coming from its
side a song a song is really there right
we can say that a song is there how you
take the song is coming from your side
but it takes 50/50 to make it a song a
good song or a bad song doesn't matter
it takes a song of hearing and then a a
mind which takes it to be going to B am
I right this is their position okay
almost correct okay there is something
appearing and then in a way we have a
choice on how to take it we could work
with gy Michael and learn that it was
the best song you know like you could
change your perception of the song by
working on it
so the big thing in this school is
using bad things that happen to you as a
path okay they say anything can be
turned into a path you know any bad
thing that happens to you you could look
for some good in it see that's their big
deal you know okay the guy is yelling at
you he's calling you stupid that's all
right you know that's undeniable reality
there is a guy he is saying the siblings
and the dentals and the the sliding vows
that make
up you know he is there is a guy saying
words and he really existed and then
you're you're taking his words in a
certain way but you have some leeway
there you could think well maybe I can
learn something from this guy you know
like maybe I maybe occasionally I am
stupid you know or or you know you could
think I could learn something you could
there's that big thing of using uh
suffering as a p okay using suffering as
a
p would you want to be there
forever just using screw-ups as a p
you know I mean in my mind I would
rather that they just never happen so
then I don't have to be creative about
making them into a pop you see I mean
like wouldn't it be better if they just
didn't if the guy just didn't exist and
then I'm not in a position of trying to
find something useful about it you see
what I mean so we take that as a lower
school also ultimately that's a lower
view of of life you you can you know
with a lot of what do you
call gymnastics you can try to see
something good about anything but
wouldn't you much rather have the thing
never have happened anyway to have to
try to make into something good and then
so the highest School of Buddhism pranga
maima their highest School of Buddhism
they say look why don't we just try to
work it out so bad stuff never happens
in the first place okay why don't we
just stop things from happening that are
bad before they happen and then you
don't have to try to pretend that
something is is useful about this guy
wouldn't it be better to make him say
ma CH a future event which never
happens this
guy wouldn't that be nicer to to turn
into a that mean a future event which
never occurs the next time you meet I'm
talking about the next time you meet is
a future event which never
happens okay I mean that's what Nirvana
is okay that's what Nana is so what is
the higher score what do they
say this is difficult okay they say the
guy it's not that the guy is calling you
stupid and you have to interpret him in
some way
it's not that there's a real guy there
who's talking and you only have latitude
to interpret him in a certain way uh
everything about him has come from you
everything about him is already your
interpretation hearing his vowels and
consonants as criticism is already
interpretation the fact of his colors
and the shapes and his body are already
you you already making those not that
you're taking him in a certain way he is
the creation of your
mind and then they say but he is
projected outside of you okay catch this
this is delicate okay your your kic
seeds are opening and throwing an object
outside of you a perception of a guy
who's separate from you and there are
whole books uh by Dharma written to
prove that there exist other people who
are not part of your own mind okay and
your mind they did come from karmic
seeds in your
mind but your mind the seed in your mind
has ripened as an outside event they are
outside of you they're not in your head
you are not living in your head you are
creating all the people around you but
they are around you and they are not
inside you okay you you are creating all
the people and things you see but they
are not inside you you are creating them
has outside of you so therefore they are
outside of you okay so what would be the
highest way now we're at the end okay we
have one more minute not really
um what would be the
highest uh Viewpoint to take when a
person is calling you stupid what is the
Viewpoint that could get you to Nirvana
fastest because that's what we want to
talk about how could you remove your
anger forever What viewpoint of the
person who's criticizing you would allow
you to remove them
forever just understand that I created
them how in the case of someone calling
you
stupid I must have called someone
something similar in the past okay if
you want to if you don't like them and
if you would like to get rid of people
like that in your life what would be the
only
way stop calling people stupid or
similar types of work okay
and that's all that's the end of the
story what
happens what happens if you stop
responding slowly one by one the karmas
the sanskaras which create irritating
people in your
world they'll just wear out and there's
no one to replace them there's no new
ones and then slowly one by one you
become surrounded by beautiful people
and that's
new okay that's Nirvana there comes a
point because you haven't responded
because you didn't want to plan a new
stupid guy that you that you work
yourself to
Nirvana and then you're just happy all
the time and you're just surrounded by
beautiful extraordinary people all the
time and you make it that way okay got
it that's the highest Viewpoint right so
um that's all tomorrow you have an
exam uh which was
oh you were going to see how it felt to
do the opposite I think am I right yeah
okay so I'm going to for example in my
case I'm going
to I'm going to be jealous of somebody
I'm going to catch myself being jealous
and then I'm going to try to think about
something about them which I would
celebrate and then I would compare how
that feels to being
jealous okay the how it makes me feel
for the next few hours okay got it
that's your assignment
I I don't have to check to see if you've
done your assignment
because I just see how happy you look if
you don't look happy I know you didn't
try cuz it makes you happy all right
okay it's like automatic
exam the more grumpy people the less
people we missing all right tomorrow I
think we're going to do I for uh oh
we're going to talk about you
know what mean to stop the wheel of
rebirth you know if Nirvana means uh I'm
not reborn anymore I was talking to
Jigme she said the first time she heard
that she got scared she said well where
am I going to be after that and I think
most of us that's across your mind right
like if if Nirvana means that whe rever
stops then what happens to GUI Michael I
might prefer just to
stay okay what does it mean to stop the
wheel and rebirth and where would you be
after that where do you go after that
okay would that
[Applause]
tomorrow I'd like to thank very much G
mro let's give him a big hand